<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and plaine narration of proceedings at an assemsemblie [sic] in Glasco, 8. Iun. 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-governement With a narration of some straunge episcopall accidents lately happened in Scotland, worthie co[n]sideration: which the wise of heart will vnderstand.</title>
            <title>Briefe and plaine narration of proceedings at an assemblie in Glasco, 8. Iun. 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-governement.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838905</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838905</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3295</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3295)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1139:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and plaine narration of proceedings at an assemsemblie [sic] in Glasco, 8. Iun. 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-governement With a narration of some straunge episcopall accidents lately happened in Scotland, worthie co[n]sideration: which the wise of heart will vnderstand.</title>
                  <title>Briefe and plaine narration of proceedings at an assemblie in Glasco, 8. Iun. 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-governement.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of Latin verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A brief narration of proceedings at an assemblie in Glasco.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A briefe and plaine Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of proceedings at an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſemblie in <hi>Glaſco,</hi> 8. Iun. 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>With a narration of ſome ſtraunge Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall accidents lately happened in Scotland, worthie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration: which the wiſe of heart will vnderſtand.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſalm 2.6.</bibl>
               <p>I have for my King opon Zion.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Proverb 21.30.</bibl>
               <p>There is no counſell againſt the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke 19.37.</bibl>
               <p>Thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould reigne over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Anno 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:2"/>
            <head>To the reverend Brethren in Scotlande.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I can not (as I often deſired) ſee with my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes, by what meanes &amp; degrees the ſtate of Christ his Church (there) is become ſo ſtraungelie defaced, that ſo I might with more feeling pray, and with more iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t helpe, as <hi>I</hi> could: yet have I never cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> carefully to hearke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after, &amp; diligently to inquire concerning Ieruſalem. So that (of late) by ſundrie intelligences, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that the <hi>Glorie of the Lord,</hi> (can <hi>Nehemiah</hi> poſsibly hold in his teares?) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from that part of Iſraell touching out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward administration of Christ his Kingdome by his owne Office-bearers. Oh, that our ſinnes have provoked God thus to moove our <hi>David</hi> against vs! We hoped that our gratious King (according to his promiſe made openly in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingburgh</hi> that day before he went towardes England) would rather have remooved thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3295:3"/>Reliques of Antichrist, which ever have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the peace of Chriſt his church in England, wherevnto the God of peace did carrie him in a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull peace, that he ſhould prove a Prince of peace in building and beautifying the houſe of God. O thou highest, and most gracious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of kings, who diddest turue our Kings heart in Anno Dom. 1592. torestore Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, notwithſtanding he had in anno <hi>1584.</hi> ſet vp Papall Biſhops: give him now grace religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie to remember, That he hath by ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſworne to defende Diſcipline then in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, all the dayes of his life, and That hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to a constitution of the generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie in <hi>Holi-rud</hi> houſe. And anno <hi>1602.</hi> where by it was ordayned (to prevent aſpiring to the ſtate of Papall Biſhops in Englande) that thoſe who were called by his Maieſtie vnto that Parleament, and were formerlie intituled Lord Biſhoppes, ſhould from thence-forward, have no longer that title, and be called <hi>Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the Kirk to vote in Parleament.</hi> Longe have we (in theſe partes) expected from ſome of you (in whom the holy fire is not yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed)
<pb facs="tcp:3295:3"/>a continuance of the <hi>faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port anent th'aſſemblie at Aberdene</hi> But ſuppoſing that eyther <hi>feare,</hi> or want of meanes hath reſtreigned your zealous ſpirites, I have out of the ſaid intelligences compiled this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with all faithfulnes, though perhaps, there may be ſome ſmall miſtaking of the order of time. For most of myne intelligences (which I followe) ſhewe that the Archbiſhop of Glaſco preached first. But one reported the Biſhoppe of Orkney to be the firſte preacher. It is thought meete by moe then my ſelfe to publiſh it, in hope, That, through the mercifull working of our good Lord and God, it may occaſion our wyſe &amp; Chriſtian King (according to that heavenlie light, wherewith God hath indued him) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive and redreſſe ſuch ſhamefull proceedings. 2. The Nobles, Barons, and Burroughes, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that if ſuch proceedings holde on, manie (beſides the Engliſhe Nation) will (too readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) ſaye: <hi>Are the Nobles, Barons, and Borroughes of Scotland (as well as the Biſhopps and ſome Miniſters there) cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the treaſure of Englande, to
<pb facs="tcp:3295:4"/>yeelde vnto the ouerthrowinge of their Law, by directions from England, which proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inſtigations of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>torbuie? 3.</hi> The periured hyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and apoſtate betrayers of Chriſt his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to repent, if they have ſo much grace, or to be aſhamed, if they be not paſt all grace, the wages of vnrighteouſnes choking the ſpirit of God in them. And <hi>4.</hi> Such faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt Ieſus, as fight the good fight of faith, to iuſtifie Wiſedome, by learned and modeſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, to reſiſt the approches of Antichsiſt, by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſuffering, though vnto bloud: and inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantlie to pray to God of trueth (who hath ſaid to his Chriſt, <hi>Sit thou at my right hande, vntill I make thine enemies thy foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole)</hi> to take his owne cauſe into his owne handes, &amp; to make our Noble King (all ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes notwithstandinge) a worthie inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his glorie herein. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:4"/>
            <head>A briefe and plaine narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of proceedings at an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie in <hi>Glaſco,</hi> 8. Iune 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall Aſſemblie at <hi>Linlithgowe</hi> 26. Iuli, 1608. appointed 10. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the preſent kirk governement, and 10. affecting the Hierarchie of Lord Biſhoppes, to conferre about middeſſes, to determine queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted among Miniſters, but referred the determination it ſelfe to the next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly then and there agreed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon touching tyme and place, and that with conſent of <hi>Dumbar</hi> the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, according to the Statute. Theſe 20. met at <hi>Falklande.</hi> The Biſhops would have made a queſtion, whether the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of the Kirk by Synodes and
<pb facs="tcp:3295:5"/>Preſbiteries, or by the Biſhopps, were more agreeable to the word of God. The other ſide would not yeelde to make a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that point, becauſe the preſent Kirk governement by Synodes and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteries was without controverſie eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Parleament and former Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, &amp; further confirmed by the Oathes of his Maieſtie, the Nobles &amp; Miniſters. And therefore without the compaſſe of their commiſſion from the general Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blies The Biſhops being defeated of their purpoſe (which was ſuſpending the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> if queſtion had been made thereof, as may appeare by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell) the conference was ſo adiorned, that it never helde againe, neither the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſemblie, though by ſuch lawfull conſent appointed for ſome weekes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt day appointed, it was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by proclamation. And why? If it had convened in dewe order, then everie Presbiterie ſhould have freely choſen 2. or 3. of the ſame to be Commiſsioners for
<pb facs="tcp:3295:5"/>the generall Aſſemblie, and (in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) would have given them ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to bee obſerved vppon payne of Nullitie on their proceeding, and of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and excommunication, if they proceeded otherwiſe, as all the Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries did in one forme at the ſaide former aſſemblie, viz. that they ſhould not give their conſent to anie alteration of the Kirk governement, &amp;c. All this being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings purpoſe, it pleaſed his Maieſtie to ſende <hi>Dumbar</hi> (a man after his owne heart) with a multitude of Letters, ſome to ſeverall Presbyteries, and ſome to particular perſons, ſuch as could readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſaie, Placer. The Biſhopps (forſooth) accompanied everie Biſhop in his owne Dioceſſe: the Kings letters, with theirs to the Presbiterie, as if the Kings Letters were not ſufficient without theirs. The parport of both letters was peremptorilie to charge the Presbiteries, to ſende to the Aſſemblie to be at Glaſco 8. Iunij. that verie man whom the King named, and in
<pb facs="tcp:3295:6"/>no ſorte to give them direction, that they might be free to vote as the King &amp; they them ſelves would.</p>
            <p>Before the Aſſemblie (or rather Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie) convened, <hi>Dumbar</hi> and the Biſhops had three dayes ſerious conference to plott all matters: when thoſe tractable men were come, <hi>Dumbar</hi> honorablie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayned them with <hi>Balaams</hi> wages (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>ſub nomine viatici</hi>) as he had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie intertayned the like Aſſemblie at <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lithgowe</hi> Anno 1606. at what time <hi>(vijs &amp; modis)</hi> he ſet vp a conſtant Moderator, to make way for a Lord Biſhop to be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in fulnes of time, whiche was even nowe. For as <hi>Daniel,</hi> vnderſtandinge by bookes, that the time of captivitie was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, faſted and prayed that Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might returne to their owne lande, ſo the Apoſtolicall (I ſhould ſay) Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prelates, knowing by certayne intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, that the time of caſting off Chriſt his yoke was come, faſted and prayed (I ſay not by Daniels ſpirit) thus Lordly, or
<pb facs="tcp:3295:6"/>(as the King calles them) Papall Biſhops, might Dominere over the Lords inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The firſt that preached was the Archbiſhop of <hi>Glaſco,</hi> his text was, Ier. 51.9. <hi>We would have cured Babel, &amp;c.</hi> This hee applied onely to <hi>Rome.</hi> But why did not the Archb. applie it thus: So wee would haue repaired <hi>Babel,</hi> that is the Hierarchie of Papall Biſhopps, which is a principall tower of that great Cittie which ruleth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Kings? Belike <hi>Dumbar</hi> &amp; the Biſhops had appointed that parte to be played by other. For the ſeconde Preacher was the Biſhop of <hi>Oarkeny,</hi> whoſe text was, Rom. 14.19. <hi>Let vs followe thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne peace:</hi> He ſhewed that peace is kept by keping Truth. But whereas Truth tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the authoritie of Biſhops over Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteries, was contraverted, He taught that Prelaticall truth thus: What greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the practiſe of the Apoſtles and the conſent of the primitive Church, with authoritie of old and new Fathers, as <hi>Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Iunius, Calvin, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, it is of it
<pb facs="tcp:3295:7"/>ſelfe eyther indifferent, or commmaunded, or contrarie to the word: it can not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different none (he thinkes) can ſhewe it to be contrarie to the word. Therefore it muſt be commaunded in the word. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, it hath the commaund of our mightie King, who for knowledge of Theologie, exceedeth farre all the Doctors of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Therefore what ingratitude ſhall it be to vs to refuſe ſo neceſſarie a law, a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to vs Biſhops, but to the Kirk of God the onely perfection of hir libertie in this life. This done, the people were diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a while. In which ſpace the diſſemblie chooſeth the Archb. of Glaſco Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and a privie conference (whiche En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhmen call a Comittie) vppon which were <hi>Dumbar,</hi> the Biſhops, many States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſome deemed oppoſites to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as <hi>M. Hall, M. Copar, &amp;c.</hi> The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop produced the K. Letters, wherein he profeſſed care to maintaine diſcipline, whereof his Ma. ever thought Biſhops to be the ground and piller, And therefore
<pb facs="tcp:3295:7"/>hath convocated the Diſſemblie to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them in their ful power, having long wayted and looked that the Presbiteries ſhold have done it of themſelves. Behold here Prelaticall Theologie. Beholde the Prelats faſt, In the midſt of the pretended humbling their ſoules in a ſolemne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: before the King of Kings, an earthlie Kings letter muſt be read, elections muſt bee made, they muſt fall to their buſines, before they have ended their faſting and prayer for direction and a bleſſing, But confuſed proceedings are fitt for a worke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion intended. Well at laſt they go to the third Sermon made by Doct. <hi>Hodge ſone</hi> (one of Dumbar his Engliſh Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines) his text was, Act. 2.1. his doctrine of cookes and kitching ſtuffe. And yet hee had one argument of note for the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie of L. Biſhops, viz. Chriſt taught ſome of his Apoſtles at the head, ſome in his boſome, and ſome at his feete, <hi>Ergo,</hi> potlid. The next day being Satterdy, the diſſemblie convened about 8. houres, but
<pb facs="tcp:3295:8"/>ſate looking one on another, till about el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven; The cauſe was oppoſition in the privie conference betweene <hi>Maist. Iohn Hall,</hi> &amp;c. and the Biſhops about their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voyce in Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Biſhopsoath to the contrarie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vrged, <hi>Dumbar</hi> produced a Lettre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King to the Biſhopps, commaunding them eyther to accept their whole office, or to quite their places: So were the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopps freed from their oath, the matter therevpon preſentlie carried with plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of voyces, and then they went to the Aſſemblie, wherein nothing was done that forenoone, onely the Archbiſhoppe being Moderator, excuſed the longe ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the privie conference, and <hi>M. Prim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros</hi> would have proteſted againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of that Diſſemblie, but was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by the Moderator, becauſe it was high dinner time, and referred to the privie conference, after that <hi>Glaſco</hi> (the Diſſemblie then riſen) had drawne him to diſcover his purpoſe. In the afternoone
<pb facs="tcp:3295:8"/>the privie conference met, and make vpp their concluſions, viz. 1. The Aſſemblie at <hi>Abirdeen</hi> was vnlawful. 2. All power of convening, &amp; diſcharging generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, pertayneth only to the King. 3. Ordination, admiſſion, deprivation, &amp; ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pention. 4. Viſitation of Churches, and 5. Excommunication and abſolution be proper to the Biſhopps: if they be ſlacke, the generall Aſſemblie ſhall trie &amp; report to his Ma. that he may cenſure them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their merit. 6. Synodes are to meete yearelie in October, and April, and the Biſhopp is to bee Moderator. 7. The Presbiterian Moderator, is to bee the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop him ſelfe, or ſhalbe choſen with his conſent. 8. Miniſters admitted, ſhall give the oath of obedience to the King &amp; his Ordinarie. 9. Whoſoever ſhall preach, write, or ſpeak againſt theſe concluſions, ſhalbe deprived. The Moderator pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded theſe to the Diſſemblie, not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verallie to bee diſcuſſed, but altogether ioyntlie as one, requiring every one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb facs="tcp:3295:9"/>yea, or no: having made way to the firſt, with this reaſon: The brethren bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, have promiſed to confeſſe a fault to his Maieſtie, if they ſhalbe condemned by a generall Aſſemblie, and ſo to returne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o their owne Congregation. O reaſon Archiepiſcopall! But what if the baniſhed brethren proteſt againſt this diſſemblie, &amp; pleade that they be vniuſtlie condemned, becauſe they be not heard what they can ſay for them ſelves.</p>
            <p>The Moderator likewiſe deſired the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, that a letter might be penned to requeſt his Ma. for a yearelie Aſſemblie, orat the leaſt to appointe certen tymes, as hee ſhould thinke expedient. Beholde a Machevillian trick, by a prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Synode to weaken the authoritie of Parliament in a Statute made in anno 1592. whereby it is ordayned, that there ſhould be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſemblie at leaſt once every yeare, and to give the King onely all authoritie to call generall Aſſemblies at his pleaſure, hat ſtatute notwithſtanding. Moreover,
<pb facs="tcp:3295:9"/>before their votes was particularly dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, an ordinarie was made that none ſhould ſpeak but ſpeared at. When votes were demanded, the affirmatives carried all before them, but ſome negatives char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the concluſions to bee contrarie to Gods word: Some pleaded their oath to maintayne Diſcipline ſo many yeres eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and ſome anſwered, they had no commiſſion from their Presbiteries. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, theſe concluſions get the more ready paſſage, becauſe a feare was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that <hi>Dumbar</hi> had the Kinges guarde preſent to commit ſuch as ſhould earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie withſtand the Kings purpoſe. For his Lo. profeſſed that he would have no man there that ſhould give cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Laſtlie, to make all ſure, there were in this diſſemblie beſides the 13. Biſh. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles 13. and Gentlemen 40. which were not choſen by Synodes or Presbyteries to carrie the matter with pluralitie of votes, if in aunters, many Miniſters ſhould ſtand for their presbiteries, al other deviſes not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.
<pb facs="tcp:3295:10"/>When this tranſcendent au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie of papall Biſh. was thus obtained, <hi>Dumbar</hi> produced an inſtrument fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King, vtterlie to diſcharge al the Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. If queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ben made in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at <hi>Faulkland</hi> before mentioned of the then preſent kirk-government, would not <hi>Dumbar</hi> have plaid the pranke even then to ſuſpend the excom. therof? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſcharge of Presbiteries was red, ther was an outcry in the Aſſemblie: <hi>Dumbar</hi> tooke that occaſion to promiſe vppon his honor, to perſwade the King, if he could, to recall that diſcharge: Provided they would ſubſcribe the concluſions whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented. By this cunning he got the hands aſwell as the votes of manie ſworne <hi>Balamits.</hi> The next day being Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, the Kings Chaplaines <hi>D. Hampton</hi> &amp; <hi>D. Merdon,</hi> preached one in the forenone, t'hother in the afternoone. <hi>D. Hamptons</hi> text was, Pſal. 122.1. <hi>I reioyced. &amp;c.</hi> In his doctrine hee taxed ſacrilegious perſons, who robbed God of his tenthes, reproved
<pb facs="tcp:3295:10"/>the forme of Diſcipline by Synodes and Presbiteries, &amp; proved the ſuperiorities of Biſhops thus: To one maintaining paritie, another ſaid, begin paritie in your owne houſe, <hi>Ergo</hi> the ſtaffe ſtands in the church conner. <hi>M. Moret.</hi> text was, 2 Cor. 1.12. <hi>Our reioycing is the teſtimonie of a good conſcience.</hi> A principall part of his doctrine was, a maintenance of ſuperioritie of Biſhops, with theſe reaſons: 1. There was ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie amongſt Prieſts in the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 2. Though the high Prieſt was a type of Chriſt, yet there were Captaines over the Prieſtes &amp; Levites. 3. Paul left Titus at <hi>Creta</hi> to ordaine Elders, and it is not ſaid. I leave thee an Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt. 4. Act. 20.28. &amp; Revel. 2.1. conferred togither. <hi>5. Bees</hi> and <hi>Cranes</hi> have their governors, yea Angells have <hi>Gabriel,</hi> &amp; Devills have <hi>Belzebub</hi> their princes, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Pope is no oecumenicall Biſhop. On Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day the Moderator pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God for the happie ſucceſſe in the firſt cauſe of that diſſemblie propounded. 2. Moe, viz. Taking order with papiſtes, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3295:11"/>proviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Miniſters, touching the which <hi>Dumbar</hi> &amp; 4. Biſhops ſhould meete, make vp a roll of excommunicants &amp; vnpla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted churches, and ſende it to the King. So the diſſemblie was diſmiſſed, now new appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; Pſal. 133. chanted. As <hi>Dumber,</hi> Biſh. Noble men, and others returned by <hi>Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> M. <hi>Patrik Symſon</hi> made ſuch a ſermon as grieved them at the hart, but nothing was ſaide vnto him. At their comming to <hi>Eding.</hi> M. <hi>Walter Bakanquell</hi> made a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſermon againſt the whole proceeding of the diſſemblie, for which he was called before the Counſell. But diſmiſſed with admonition, and M. <hi>Patrike Galloway</hi> in his firſt ſermon after his returne to <hi>Edingbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> from <hi>Perth.</hi> (where hee had beene all the time of the Aſſemblie) inveyed (though wiſelie yet ſenſiblie) againſt the diſſemblie, and threatned iudgementes, becauſe of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:11"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>BEfore I had altogither finiſhed the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing of this Narratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I received from a faithfull Brother (whoſe being is where be may have preſent &amp; certaine intelligence) a letter: Wherein he crediblie reporteth theſe inſuing workes of God. Which, becauſe they be right worthie to be noted, I thought good to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh in the ſame wordes, as they came to my handes. Admoniſhing our Papall Biſhoppes of the newe erection, to conſider theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: and withall to remember the death of the late titular Biſhop Maister <hi>Iames Nicholſon,</hi> who was then troubled in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for accepting that title: So that hee would not be called Biſhopp in his will, and by his Will reiected whatſoever was due to him out of his Biſhopricke. The Lord give vs vnderſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>Th' Arbiſhop of S. <hi>Androis,</hi> repoſing in his bedd in time of the afternoones ſermon, the Sabbath after his Dioceſan Synode in S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drois,</hi> was wakened and all the Kirk &amp; Towne with him, with a crie of bloud and murder. For
<pb facs="tcp:3295:12"/>his ſisters ſonne (maister of his houſholde) wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a throw of his dagger killed his Cooke, while as he was buſie in dreſsing of the Lord Biſhoppes Supper, the dagger light iust vnder the leſt pappe of the Cooke, who fell downe dead imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie.</p>
            <p>Item, the ſaid Biſhopp, at the Towne of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> in <hi>Lawdien,</hi> where hee keepit an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Dioceſan Synode: after he had bene in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine much vpon the contradiction of <hi>Core,</hi> out of the Epistle of <hi>Iude,</hi> comminge furth of the Kirk dore, in the porch thereof, the earth vnder him, burſt, and rent, and he ſunke down: So that, if he had not bene pulled out quicklie by his Colateralles, hee had gone the way of <hi>Core,</hi> and his companions.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3295:12"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
